Okay,
so today's דף daf is ע"ז. ayin-zayin. We pick up at the
bottom of ע"ז ayin-zayin עמוד ב. amud-bet. We had just quoted an
extremely long ברייתא, braita, and now we are looking at unpacking it.
So we pick up
with אמר מר. amar mar. Let's take a look. I'll find it
in a minute.
Okay.
אמר מר, amar mar, it is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, 10, 12 lines from the bottom. Last word on
the line is ממנו, mimenu, it's like four words in. It's just
above where it says שם ד' sham daled in the left-hand margin.
ע"ז ayin-zayin עמוד ב. amud-bet. You got it Risca? Okay. אמר מר.
amar mar. So now we're going to unpack that ברייתא. braita. והקריב
ממנו. Bikriv mimenu. So this is about figuring out all about the
breads of the תודה. toda. You shall bring from it, ממנו, mimenu,
מן המחובר, min hamichubar, from what is connected, which again רש"י Rashi
says means all in the same basket is when you do the
separation so it stays basically all next to each other, not literally
in the same basket. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה דכתיב,
ella me-atta de-chtiv, if that's what the word ממנו mimenu means when
the תורה Torah says את כל חלבו ירים ממנו, et kol chelbo
yarim mimenu,
you should lift up all the fat from it from the
sacrifice, התם נמי מאי מחובר איכא? hatam nami mai michubar ika? There
too what do you mean by מחובר? michubar? Of course there's מחובר,
michubar, you know, it's all connected. You're taking the fat out of
the animal. So תוספות Tosafot says well that's exactly the point, the
point is that it's so obvious, why did the תורה Torah have
to say מן המחובר, min hamichubar, right, because it's clearly where else
are you taking the fat except from out of the animal so
of course it's connected.
So what are we learning from that? So the גמרא Gemara says
כי דרב חסדא, ki de-Rav Chisda, we learn what רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says, דאמר
רב חסדא אמר אבימי, de-amar Rav Chisda amar Avimi, שלא ינתח בשר
קודם שיטול אימוריו, she-lo yenateach basar kodem she-yitol emurav, exactly that point,
don't first chop up the meat and then take the fat away.
So first essentially take the pieces of meat away and then you're
left with the fat. When you remove the fat to burn on
the altar, then you should be removing it while it's still part
of one whole with the קרבן. korban. So yes, exactly that point,
that ממנו mimenu means מחובר michubar and you take it when you
remove it from being a full unit. Okay, very nice. Which by
the way you know I mean the point here actually is I
mean we shouldn't lose sight of the point, it's not just a
technical issue, it really is the point about communicating the concept of
תרומה, terumah, something that is separated off from a larger whole that
is to be given to God as the choice maybe even. The
whole idea of the fat, right, if you were to have first
chopped up the meat and then you'd have a lot of different
pieces and here's your fat and you give your fat, then it's
just a thing you're giving to God. It's not somehow representing this
is the gift from the whole קרבן, korban, or particularly this is
the choice of the קרבן, korban, the best of the קרבן, korban,
חלב chelev is used to represent that. So the same is true
when you give תרומה. terumah. You don't just give some grain to
a כהן, kohen, you give a gift from the entire grain. It's
the ממנו mimenu and the same here from the loaf of the
ten breads. So the idea of מחובר michubar is not just a
technicality, it really is important in framing the concept of תרומה terumah
here. Okay, so that's the idea of מחובר. michubar. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, now we go on. אמר מר. amar
mar. נאמר כאן תרומה ונאמר בתרומת מעשר תרומה. nemar kan terumah ve-nemar
be-terumat ma'aser terumah. It says here תרומה terumah and it says by
תרומת מעשר, terumat ma'aser, תרומה, terumah, and that's how we learn the
idea that it is one loaf out of ten. So the גמרא
Gemara says ונילף מתרומת מדין? ve-neilef mi-trumat Midyan? Please could you go
to the other room?
So why don't we learn from מדין? Midyan? Now by מדין Midyan
it uses the phrase תרומה terumah and it says there one out
of five hundred. Remember there they gave a תרומה terumah from all
of their booty and they gave you know one out of fifty,
one out of five hundred. It's a much different proportion than the
idea of one out of ten. So let's learn out from there.
So the גמרא Gemara says דנים תרומה הנוהגת לדורות מתרומה הנוהגת לדורות.
danim terumah hanohaget ladorot mi-trumah hanohaget ladorot.
No,
we learn both the idea of תרומת מעשר terumat ma'aser is something
that applies for later generations as the idea of the תרומה terumah
from the breads of the תודה, toda, ואל תוכח תרומת מדין, ve-al
tochich trumat Midyan,
let's not learn out from the gift that they gave from the
booty of מדין Midyan שאינה נוהגת לדורות, she-eina nohaget ladorot, that
it was a one-time thing, it's not a general rule or law.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay, ונילף מתרומת חלה? ve-neilef mi-trumat challah?
It says תרומה terumah by חלה. challah. That's a gift to the
כהן kohen and there the חז"ל, chazal, at least the תורה Torah
doesn't say but חז"ל chazal say it's one in twenty-four. Always these
questions are if that's only a rabbinic שיעור shiur how can we
learn out from there, and there always is a little bit of
this tension that maybe it is a rabbinic שיעור shiur but maybe
they're trying to capture the תורה's Torah idea of what the right
amount is. So therefore let's learn out from there that it's not
one in ten but one in twenty-four. So the גמרא Gemara says
תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל. tana devei Rabbi Yishmael. They switch gears on the side. דנים
דבר שנאמר בו ממנו תרומה לה'. danim davar she-ne'emar bo mimenu terumah
l'Hashem. מדבר שנאמר בו ממנו תרומת השם. midavar shene'emar bo mimenu trumat
Hashem. Okay, so they both say the words ממנו. mimenu. This is
essentially what the ברייתא braita says. Yes, both of them say תרומה,
truma, but they also have the extra word ממנו mimenu לאפוקי תרומת
חלה l'afukei trumat challah
which excludes the case of the תרומת חלה. trumat challah. Please turn
this sound down, I don't want that to happen again. Which excludes
the case of the תרומת חלה trumat challah דלא נאמר בו ממנו
תרומה לה'. d'lo ne'emar bo mimenu truma l'Hashem. It
doesn't have the word ממנו. mimenu. Okay, so that's it. Now we're
done at least for the interim for unpacking this ברייתא braita and
we've got basically figured out that the תרומה truma means one in
ten. We learn from other פסוקים psukim that each loaf is that
once we learn that, we learn that there are ten loaves and
then we go on to learn that each loaf is an איסרון.
issaron. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara gets to a certain analysis about
what is exactly the status of this thing that is given to
the כהן. Kohen. So let's take a look. בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava,
so רבא Rava asks the following question: תרומת לחמי תודה חייבין עליה
מיתה וחומש או אין חייבין עליה מיתה וחומש? trumat lachmei todah chayavin
aleha mita v'chomesh o ein chayavin aleha mita v'chomesh? So here's a
fascinating question, right? These breads of the תודה todah are given to
a כהן Kohen and they're called תרומה. truma. How literally do you
mean that? And this is like a great example of sort of
how a Halachic mind reads certain words as opposed to how you
know just like you know the פשט. pshat. Maybe the word תרומה
truma is a generic word, it means a gift. So yeah, the
תורה Torah uses the word תרומה truma to describe the gift from
חלה challah meaning it's something that is להרים, l'harim, that is lifted
up, that is separated from a larger amount. That's what we just
said the מחובר mechubar idea. So you give the gift of grain
to the כהן, Kohen, you take a gift, a lifting up from
the חלה challah you give it to the כהן. Kohen. ביכורים bikurim
is called תרומה, truma, it's a gift to the כהן. Kohen. So
this is also a תרומה. truma. But רבא Rava with a Halachic
mindset, תרומה truma refers
classically specifically to the amount of grain given to a כהן Kohen
and there are הלכות halachot that relate to תרומה. truma. If a
non-כהן Kohen eats it you're חייב מיתה chayav mita if it's eaten
בידי שמיים. b'yedei shamayim. If it's eaten בשוגג b'shogeg you replace it
and you add a fifth. Do these things apply
to this gift of the bread to the כהן Kohen which is
also called a תרומה? truma? So let's take a look.
Why wouldn't they?
Why wouldn't they? Well I think exactly for the reason that I
said that it's
not maybe the word תרומה truma here means generic not technical. I
guess you would ask me otherwise because they also they do apply
the תרומה truma status to the other things I just
mentioned, to ביכורים, bikurim, to the חלה, challah, to תרומת מעשר. trumat
ma'aser. But all of those are at least classic in the sense
that it is a standard gift that is given from the grain.
You get this grain, you get this bounty, this produce from God
and therefore you give a gift from it to the כהן. Kohen.
So there's a תרומה truma you give to the כהן. Kohen. If
you make חלה challah you give another gift to the כהן. Kohen.
If it's the fruit and the ביכורים bikurim you give it as
a gift. But all of that is in a sense a standard
obligatory gift from the agricultural
produce given to God but through God's representative as the כהן. Kohen.
By the לחמי תודה, lachmei todah, it's completely optional. If you happen
to be bringing a קרבן תודה, korban todah, bring these loaves with
it. So it's not at all sort of similar to those other
types of agricultural gifts which are standard and mandatory.
So I think because it's optional...
well because it's optional and because it's not coming as a way
of thanks for the agricultural bounty. It's coming because I'm bringing a
תודה todah and for some reason with a תודה todah comes a
lot of bread. So and it's not a תרומה truma from what
grew from my field. It's a תרומה truma from my forty loaves
of bread. So conceptually I think it's operating in a different sort
of universe than the other תרומה. truma.
Exactly so what you're saying is it's like an addition to one
is mandatory that the fact that the person is observing the Jewish
concept and the above is a bounty as an expression of showmanship
or... right.
No, I mean the classic תרומה truma is obligatory, it's a result
of what grows in the field, it's a way of giving a
gift to God or to the כהן Kohen through what grows in
the field and so on. That's classic תרומה. truma. Here, it comes
to an optional קרבן. korban. It's not coming on its own accord,
it comes as something that attends the קרבן. korban. It's coming, the
תרומה truma is not in reference to what grew, the תרומה truma
is in reference to the other forty loaves that I'm bringing. I
just think it's very conceptually different.
So did this develop out of it or was it in...
no, in the תורה Torah it's just the word used, it just
means a gift.
Okay. No, so that's the question. So בעי רבא ba'ei Rava תרומת
לחמי תודה חייבין עליה מיתה וחומש או אין חייבין עליה מיתה וחומש?
trumat lachmei todah chayavin aleha mita v'chomesh o ein chayavin aleha mita
v'chomesh? If you eat it, if a non-כהן Kohen eats it, does
he number one get מיתה בידי שמיים mita b'yedei shamayim if he
eats it במזיד? b'mezid? Again מיתה בידי שמיים mita b'yedei shamayim and
does he add another fifth when he pays back if he ate
it בשוגג? b'shogeg? So do we say כיון דאיתקש לתרומת מעשר, kivan
d'itkash l'trumat ma'aser, since it's connected to the תרומת מעשר, trumat ma'aser,
כתרומת מעשר דמי k'trumat ma'aser dami it's similar to תרומת מעשר trumat
ma'aser where these laws do
apply? או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say בו וחמישיתו bo
v'chamishito that ומתו בו u'metu vo they'll die through eating it if
they eat it במזיד? b'mezid? Again מיתה בידי שמיים mita b'yedei shamayim
or its fifth they should add if they ate it בשוגג. b'shogeg.
So the "it" is on purpose. Yeah, so the 'et' means specifically
תרומת מעשר. Trumas Maaser. מיעט רחמנא. Miyit rachmana. So then the Torah
limits and it does not apply to the תרומה truma of the
loaves, it only applies to the classic תרומה truma of, you know,
תרומה, truma, תרומת מעשר trumas maaser and so on. So we don't
know the answer to that. Left as an open question. Another question.
מדמעת או אינה מדמעת? medamaat o einah medamaat? Does it create דמוע
dimua when it gets mixed up with other grain? Does it make
the other stuff forbidden and have the same type of status that
now it can only be eaten like the thing itself, only be
eaten by כהנים kohanim and not eaten out of Jerusalem and so
on? So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, that we also don't
know the answer. Now that's a funny question because the idea of
דמוע, dimua, of the status of what happens when it gets mixed
up and does it get nullified or not, is basically a rabbinic
issue, meaning biblically you need a majority and other types of statuses
are rabbinic. So it's a funny question to be asking, but nevertheless.
Okay, so that's it. So רבא Rava raised some very interesting questions
about how much is this real תרומה, truma, which the גמרא Gemara
leaves completely open. Now it goes on, back to the ברייתא. braisa.
אמר מר, Amar mar, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar תהיינה. tihyena. So the
question we had is,
how do you know really what we learned from שתי הלחם shtei
halechem as our model? Do we learn from שתי הלחם shtei halechem
the model that each loaf gets an עישרון, issaron, which is what
we do say, and there are ten loaves of חמץ, chametz, so
each one gets an עישרון? issaron? Or maybe we should learn from
שתי הלחם shtei halechem that there were a total of שתי עשרונות,
shtei esronot, so maybe here there's a total of שתי עשרונות shtei
esronot split between all of the ten loaves, but not an עישרון
issaron per loaf? So it said no, the פסוק pasuk says תהיינה.
tihyena. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי תלמודא, mai talmuda, where are
we learning this from? How is that at all relevant? So now
top of ע"ח עמוד א', Ayin Chet Amud Aleph, אמר רב יוסף
בר אבדימי, Amar Rav Yosef bar Avdimi, תהיינה כתיב. tihyena ksiv. Well,
that clarifies it. It says תהיינה. tihyena. So רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both say it's because the double י'. yud. So somehow the
double י', yud, you use the י' yud to be telling you
that it means that the same way it's the word תהיינה tihyena
is by the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, but to tell you that
it applies to ten. Ten loaves, right? So ten means so that
you get the idea of ten. So if you have one עישרון
issaron per loaf for the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, you have עשרה
עשרונות asara issronot for the ten loaves by your normal חמץ. chametz.
Okay, so that's how we know that the לחמי תודה, lachmei toda,
the ten חמץ chametz loaves, is an עישרון issaron per loaf. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says okay, I know ten, but how do
I know exactly what you're saying the ten means? The גמרא Gemara
says אימא עשרה קפיזי, eima asara kafizi, maybe not עשרה עשרונות, asara
issronot, maybe it's עשרה קפיזי asara kafizi which is a different measure.
רש"י Rashi says it's a half of a קב, kav, right? I
get the י' yud tells me ten, but how do I know
עשרה עשרונות? asara issronot? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, בעשרונות דיבר הכתוב.
be'issronot diber kasuv. No, because the Torah's unit is an עישרון. issaron.
It says that the שתי הלחם shtei halechem is שתי עשרונות, shtei
esronot, right? It says שתים שתי עשרונים. shtayim shtei esronim. The שתי
הלחם shtei halechem is two loaves, שתי עשרונות. shtei esronot. And if
the י' yud is telling me oh, there's another case that has
ten, then ten must mean עשרה עשרונות. asara issronot. That's our unit
that we're referring to. And therefore the ten loaves of חמץ chametz
of a תודה toda get עשרה עשרונות. asara issronot. Okay, so that's
how we know ten loaves of חמץ chametz get עשרה עשרונות. asara
issronot. Now the גמרא Gemara goes
on, going on in the ברייתא. braisa.
למדנו עשרה לחמץ. Lamadnu asara l'chametz. That's how you know ten loaves
of עשרה עשרונות asara issronot for the ten loaves of חמץ. chametz.
עשרה למצה מניין? Asara l'matza minayin? How do you know עשרה עשרונות
asara issronot for the מצה, matza, which was again thirty loaves? So
the same amount of flour, but here divided between thirty loaves. תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, because it's a פסוק. pasuk. It says על חלות
לחם חמץ. al chalos lechem chametz. It says bring all of these
מצות, matzos, חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן וסולת מורבכת.
chalos matzos blulos bashemen v'rikikei matzos meshuchim bashemen v'soles murbaches. So bring
all these three different types of מצה matza and then it says
על חלות לחם חמץ, al chalos lechem chametz, opposite the חמץ. chametz.
So there's an equal amount of חמץ chametz to מצה, matza, although
thirty loaves to ten loaves, the amount of flour is the same.
So if we've already said there are ten loaves of חמץ, chametz,
one עישרון issaron per loaf, עשרה עשרונות, asara issronot, and now we're
told an equal amount of מצה, matza, so while it's true there
are thirty loaves of מצה, matza, but it is the same amount
of flour, it is the עשרה
עשרונות. asara issronot. כנגד חמץ הוי מצה. Keneged chametz havei matza. Opposite
חמץ chametz bring מצה, matza, bring an equivalent amount of מצה, matza,
again not the number of loaves, that's thirty, but the similar amount
of flour. So now the גמרא Gemara does have one of you
the תוספות Tosafot has a question about whether we can do this
type of derivation. וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? V'chi davar
halamad b'hekkesh chozer u'melamed b'hekkesh? Is something that was learned from a
היקש hekkesh do we go back and teach to a היקש? hekkesh?
Because why? How do we know that the חמץ chametz gets ten
עשרה עשרונות? asara issronot? Because we learned the חמץ chametz of the
תודה toda from the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Okay, so now we
know that the חמץ chametz of the תודה toda gets the שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, that's how we learn the עשרה עשרונות. asara issronot.
Now we're going to say, oh, since the חמץ chametz gets עשרה
עשרונות, asara issronot, the מצה matza gets עשרה עשרונות. asara issronot. But
that's a problem of daisy-chaining it. גזונטהייט? Gezuntheit? Is something that you
learn from a היקש hekkesh can you now go ahead and learn
it through another היקש? hekkesh? Right, you see how we're daisy-chaining? From
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem we learned an עישרון issaron per loaf.
We linked it to the חמץ chametz of the תודה toda and
we said an עישרון issaron per loaf, עשרה עשרונות asara issronot for
the חמץ. chametz. Now we're going to link that to the מצה
matza and say עשרה עשרונות asara issronot for מצה. matza. Since when
are you allowed to do that? Since when can you daisy-chain? וכי
דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? V'chi davar halamad b'hekkesh chozer u'melamed
b'hekkesh? Is something that's learned from a היקש... hekkesh... Can something that's
learned out from one link can go ahead and teach through another
link? So the גמרא Gemara says הימנו ודבר אחר הוא. Himenu ve-davar
akher hu. No, it's from it and another thing, I'll explain that.
וכל הימנו ודבר אחר לא הוי היקש. Vekhol himenu ve-davar akher lo
hava hekesh. And if it's from it and another thing, it's not
a היקש, hekesh, which basically means I would call that if we're
calling the first thing piggyback problem, this would be the, this would
be the, no, not, the first one is the daisy chain problem,
this is the piggyback solution. Which means if you are learning you
have A, B, and C. So you take A which is the
שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you apply it to B, one עישרון isaron
per loaf, ten עשרונות. esronot. Then you take the idea from B,
ten עשרונות esronot for the חמץ chametz and you apply it to
C, the מצה. matzah. So the point is you can't do that,
you can't take A to B and then take that to C.
Ah, but if you're already learning something sort of local for B
and applying it to C, then you can שלעפ schlep along what
you learned from A. Okay? That's like a piggyback. הימנו, Himenu, you're
learning from it, ודבר אחר ve-davar akher and you're שלעפינג schlepping along
the other thing. So since we're already learning, you know, from B
to C, from the חמץ chametz to the מצה, matzah, the idea
that there are, you know, ten loaves of each genre, and that's
something, you know, that we're sort of learning and applying from B
to C. So since we're already applying something from B to C,
we can שלעפ schlep along the other thing that we learned, which
is that it's ten עשרונות esronot for the entire quantity. Okay, so
that is the answer. So now let's take a
look. Okay, so then it says like this, וכל הימנו... Vekhol himenu...
גמרא Gemara says הני למאן דאמר לא הוי היקש. Hani leman de-amar
lo hava hekesh. So that's good if you say that when you
שלעפ schlep along something else it's not really a היקש hekesh and
it's not really a problem. אלא למאן דאמר הוי היקש, Ella leman
de-amar hava hekesh, for the one who says it's still considered a
היקש hekesh and therefore you cannot do A to B and B
to C even if you're learning something local from B to C,
מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? What can you say? How do
you learn that it's an equivalent amount of flour? So גמרא Gemara
says תביאו ריבויה היא. tavyu ribuya hi. Because where did we learn
from שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem the idea of ten of an עישרון
isaron per loaf which got us ten עשרונות? esronot? Because it said
ממושבותיכם תביאו לחם תנופה שתים עשרונים. mimoshavoteichem tavyu lechem tenufah shtayim esronim.
So תביאו, tavyu, you shall bring, is construed by the גמרא Gemara
to be a very inclusive word and refers to bringing a lot
of different things. So the same way we said that therefore we
can use it to teach about the חמץ chametz part of the
תודה, Todah, because also the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is itself חמץ,
chametz, we can also learn from the תביאו tavyu that it's coming
to include a lot of things, that it's even coming to teach
us something about the מצה. matzah. So because of the word תביאו,
tavyu, it allows us to learn from the מצה. matzah. Okay, so
now we're done unpacking the ברייתא. baraita. What do we get out
of all this? We get that number one, we learned the idea
that there are ten loaves per מין min because it says תרומה
terumah and we learned from the מעשר maaser and the גמרא Gemara
said why we didn't learn from other תרומות. terumot. That it's one
loaf to the כהן, kohen, therefore there are out of ten, but
it's one loaf out of each type of bread, you know, one
חמץ, chametz, three מצות, matzos, so there's a total of 40 loaves.
One of each of the ten goes to the כהן. kohen. We
also had רבא's Rava very interesting question, what is the status of
that gift to a כהן? kohen? Is it a real status of
תרומה terumah or not? Very open-ended question, very interesting question. Then we
had the idea about how much flour goes into each loaf and
based on the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem we learned that the idea
for the חמץ chametz it's an עישרון isaron per loaf which is
ten עשרונות. esronot. For the מצה, matzah, it's actually a third of
that because it's ten עשרונות esronot for all 30 loaves, so each
loaf is actually a third the size. And then again, so therefore
for the חמץ chametz we are talking about a huge loaf of
bread. We're talking about basically a loaf of bread made out of
a five-pound bag of flour. So we're talking about one huge loaf
of bread. That was the size of the breads you were bringing
for the עומר, Omer, that would be the size of the two
loaves that you would bring for the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. There
would be this huge loaf of bread made out of an עישרון.
isaron. That's in contrast to a normal מנחה minchah which uses the
same עישרון isaron but makes out of it ten or twelve loaves
of bread. So here your single loaf is from this one bag
of flour. And that's 40 loaves, right? So you are basically bringing
with your תודה, Todah, you're bringing 40 breads made out of 20
five-pound bags of flour. You are bringing an enormous amount of bread
when you're bringing a תודה. Todah. Okay, first of all, what?
At least probably the size of this.
I mean how big is one loaf made out of a five-pound
bag of flour? One of those wedding חלות. challahs. Is it really,
is it not bigger than that? You think that's about right? I
don't know, I think it might be bigger. I think it might
be bigger, yeah. So you have ten of those wedding חלות challahs
and then an equivalent amount of מצה. matzah. And the breads themselves,
what? So that's you know, it's interesting, the גמרא Gemara before spoke
about, says that from the, you know, it's the גמרא Gemara never
sort of has a focused discussion on this, it's always sort of
referring to it. It does speak about a normal מנחה minchah that
the לישה lishah could be done by the non-כהן. kohen. It might
have had to be done in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because
of the כלי שרת, klei shares, but it could be done by
the non-כהן. kohen. The baking also the גמרא Gemara has a whole
question whether the תנור tannur was a כלי שרת klei shares or
not, but it sounds like... but that they did use the oven
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But that's one question about where
was it? In principle, it could be done by the person himself.
The כהן kohen did not have a required role until actually like
the הגשה, hagasha, the presenting to the כהן. kohen. So it might
have been that based on when the כלי שרת kli sharet was
introduced, the baking or the kneading had to be done in the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but
it could have been done by... what? All those sieves that they
needed, right?
But remember then the גמרא Gemara says that you could buy that
from a middleman, right? So a lot of this thing, right, sounds
like it's so detailed and technical, you're doing it in the מקדש,
Mikdash, and then we find out that you could buy it from
a middleman like the flour. And here too, you could bake the
stuff. There's an opinion earlier in the גמרא Gemara that it was
not using a כלי שרת, kli sharet, at least by a normal
מנחה, mincha, but the oven is a similar but different debate. But
you know in theory it could be baked even outside of the
מקדש Mikdash and then brought to the מקדש. Mikdash. But certainly it
could be done by a non-כהן, kohen, certainly even if it had
to be done in the מקדש, Mikdash, it could be done by
a non-כהן. kohen.
Supervising? Under the auspices, in other words, supervised by?
Yeah, supervised, overseen by, but even the overseen is questionable. The גמרא
Gemara never said that it has to be done in the מקדש
Mikdash so we could oversee it. And most it said a concern
about the use of the כלי שרת, kli sharet, and because the
כלי שרת kli sharet is מקדיש, makdish, you don't want it out
of the מקדש Mikdash at that time. Okay, so now let's take
a look.
Anything to add to the comment? No.
I mean, it's enough of a חידוש chiddush that we're adding water.
I'm serious. Although I will say, you know, the גמרא Gemara did
before contemplate the question about מי פירות, mei peirot, and the question
is, you know, and whether that creates חמץ chametz or not. And
the question that we raised at the time was, well, who cares
if it creates חמץ chametz or not? You know, why should it
be allowed if it's not what the תורה Torah says you're allowed
to have, you know, מצה? matzah? But that's, yeah, the גמרא, Gemara,
you know, but the basic assumption is no, though, other than water,
nothing else can go into the מצה. matzah. Exactly. Alright, so let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishna. המילואים, HaMiluim, now we'll just
have like a little historical note. המילואים היה באים כמצה שבתוודה. HaMiluim
haya baim kematzah shebaTodah. When they brought the מילואים, miluim, right, they
inaugurated the כהנים kohanim into the עבודה, avodah, they also brought, you
know,
these קרבנות korbanot with loaves. So what type of loaves did they
bring? Just like, just like that they had by the תודה. Todah.
חלות, רקיקין, ורביכה. challos, rekikin, u'rvichah. Then the, but the מצה matzah
of the תודה, Todah, they did not have any חמץ chametz loaves,
but they did have three types of מצה matzah loaves that were
with the מילואים. miluim. We'll look at the פסוקים pesukim in a
minute, which were the חלות, challos, רקיקין, rekikin, and the רביכה. revichah.
We never really have totally described how those loaves are different, but
okay. ונזירות, U'nezirus, by a נזיר, nazir, he actually brings with his
קרבן, korban, with his שלמים, shlamim, he brings certain loaves. So which
type of loaves does he bring? היתה באה שתי ידות כמצה. Hayta
ba'ah shtei yadot kematzah. So he would bring two-thirds, שתי ידות shtei
yadot means two portions, but it also means two-thirds, two-thirds of the
types of מצה matzah loaves which were brought by the תודה. Todah.
Now remember the תודה Todah has three types of מצה matzah loaves,
so by saying two, it's saying he brings two of those types.
Which two types? של אותה חלות ורקיקין. Shel otah challos u'rekikin. He
brings חלות challos and רקיקין. rekikin. Again, most of this is in
the פסוקים, pesukim, we'll see in a minute. ואין בה רבוכה. V'ein
bah revuchah. But he did not bring רביכה, revichah, which is more
like the oil-soaked type of a wafer. נמצא, Nimtza, now, how much
flour went into the מצה? matzah? We've been using the עשרון issaron
measure. We said that there were ten עשרונות isronot of flour that
went into the thirty loaves of מצה. matzah. But if you remember,
the משנה Mishna also told us that that was the, you know,
wilderness measure, you know, when they were קדשי ישראל, kodshei Yisrael, they
used a measure of different types of סאה, se'ah, but also of
קבים. kavim. And basically, ten עשרונות isronot is equal to fifteen קבים.
kavim. So it said they would have fifteen קבים kavim for the
thirty loaves, for the three types of מצה. matzah. So if the
נזיר nazir is only having two of those three types, and we're
going to assume proportional, how much flour is going to go for
the נזיר's? nazir עשרה קבין, Asara kabin, exactly, which is what the
משנה Mishna
says. עשרה קבין ירושלמיות. Asarah kabin Yerushalmiyot. There are ten of these
ירושלים Yerushalayim קבים. kavim. Again, the wilderness measure would be six and
two-thirds, you know, it'd be two-thirds of ten, but it's easier if
you're, if you're dividing by fifteen, then you have ten. Then, so
it's ten קבים, kavim, שהן ששה עשרונות ועוד יהן, shehen shisha isronot
v'od yahen, which is six plus a fraction of עשרונות. isronot. It's
not, it's actually more than not just a small fraction, it's two-thirds,
but okay. So we're just doing that math again. Ten עשרונות isronot
for these thirty loaves, a נזיר nazir that only gets two-thirds, two
of the types of מצה, matzah, not all three, gets two-thirds out
of ten עשרונות isronot of flour, which is six and two-thirds עשרונות
isronot of flour, or in the Jerusalem measures is ten קב. kav.
Ten out of, it was fifteen קב, kav, now we're down to
ten קב. kav. Alright, so let's take a look. So that's using
this as a model to discuss the מילואים miluim and the case
of the נזיר. nazir. So מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei milei? Where
do you know this from in terms of the מילואים, miluim, that
it was all these three types of מצה? matzah? So אמר רב
חסדא אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר קרא, Amar Rav Chisda amar
Rav Chama bar Guria amar kra, because the פסוק pasuk says by
the מילואים, miluim, ומסל המצות אשר לפני ה', u'misal ha-matzot asher lifnei
Hashem,
from the basket of matzot that was before God, לקח חלת מצה
אחת וחלת לחם שמן אחת ורקיק אחד. lakach challat matzah achat v'challat
lechem shemen achat v'rakik echad.
So he took again one out of each type of מצה. matzah.
And here's how it describes the three types of מצה: matzah: חלת
מצה, chalas matzah, חלת לחם שמן, chalas lechem shemen, and רקיק. rakik.
So two out of those three is easy to identify, which is
what the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא חלות חלות. Bishlama chalos chalos. When
it says חלת מצה, chalas matzah, so that's like by the תודה
Todah where it says חלות מצות. chalos matzos. So that's just the
standard חלה. chala. Okay, רקיק, rakik, which is a wafer, is a
רקיק, rakik, that's the רקיק rakik that you have by תודה, Todah,
so two out of the three we have. Now we have the
third one that's mentioned here by the מילואים Milu'in that's hard to
identify, which calls it a חלת לחם שמן. chalas lechem shemen. And
we also have something, what's the third type by the תודה? Todah?
The רבוכה. revucha. The רבוכה revucha actually is a type of a
wafer that's heavily drenched in oil. So the גמרא Gemara says, look,
we have there three types and one is called a רבוכה. revucha.
We have here three types, two out of the three we've identified,
the third one is חלת לחם שמן. chalas lechem shemen. It's logical
to assume that that means the same as the רבוכה revucha and
then it'll be the exact three parallel the three. So the גמרא
Gemara says שמן מאי ניהו? shemen mai nihu? What's this שמן, shemen,
this third type mentioned by the מילואים? Milu'in? לאו רבוכה? lav revucha?
Obviously it's got to be the רבוכה revucha which is the third
type that we have by the תודה. Todah. So that's a very
reasonable, you know, extrapolation or interpretation. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף
לה רב חביא בר רב אביא maskif lah Rav Chavya bar Rav
Avia challenges: אימא אנתא דמשחא? eima anta demishcha? How do you know
what a חלת לחם שמן chalas lechem shemen is? Who tells you
that it's parallel to the תודה? Todah? Maybe it means like a,
you know, an
oil-drenched cake? Maybe it has nothing to do with the רבוכה revucha
mentioned in the פסוק? pasuk? רש"י Rashi here, or the pseudo-רש"י, pseudo-Rashi,
makes even a more radical suggestion. He says that maybe the word
חלה chala (although it doesn't really work with the word לחם), lechem
but he says that maybe, you know, חלה, chala, a bread, a
loaf, doesn't even really refer to bread. Maybe it could refer to
using that term for some other thing and maybe it just means
like a congealed mass of oil that you would call a loaf
of oil. The problem is that it does say חלת לחם שמן.
chalas lechem shemen. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara is saying just
because it calls one thing oily bread and you have this other
thing in this other case that's called a רבוכה, revucha, it's attractive
to say it's the same idea, but who tells you? Maybe it's
a different thing, maybe it's a type of an oily cake, it's
not similar at all.
So what is the word אנתא? anta?
Apparently it means some type of a cake, that's what רש"י Rashi
says. I have not seen that word before and I don't know
if it appears anywhere else, but רש"י Rashi says here, let's see
what רש"י Rashi says, he says
עוגה של שמן. uga shel shemen. Okay, there you go.
So I can't tell you where else it appears, first time I'm
seeing it. אלא, Ela, so the גמרא Gemara says כדדרש נחמן בר
רב חסדא kedidrash Nachman bar Rav Chisda משמיה דרב תבלא, mishmei deRav
Tavla, so like רב נחמן בר חסדא Rav Nachman bar Chisda says
in the name of רב תבלא, Rav Tavla, זה קרבן אהרן ובניו
אשר יקריבו להשם, zeh korban Aharon uvanav asher yakrivu laHashem, this is
the קרבן korban of אהרן Aharon and his sons that they will
bring to God ביום המשח אותו, beyom hamishach oso, when they are
anointed, and so on. Now that is telling you what they brought
when they had the מילואים. Milu'in. It's also telling you, by the
way, something we haven't discussed, that
when any כהן kohen gets ready to serve in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and it's the first time he's serving in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he brings a קרבן, korban, a מנחה mincha to
be מחנך mechanech in the עבודה, avoda, to basically be his initiation
in the עבודה. avoda. And that's what also we learn from this
פסוק pasuk about ביום המשח אותו, beyom hamishach oso, that in the
future when a כהן kohen starts to do the עבודה, avoda, he
brings a type of a מנחה mincha like this. We'll talk about
that in a minute. Okay, and therefore, but it also, by referring
to the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, אהרן ובניו, Aharon uvanav, remember the
כהן גדול kohen gadol brings every day a מנחה, mincha, half in
the morning and half in the afternoon. So we're going to ask
how are these ideas being linked. So it says like this, וכי
מה למדנו לבניו ביום המשחו? vechi mah lamadnu levanav beyom hamishacho? How,
why are we connecting his sons and their קרבן korban to the
anointing of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, which it understands to mean
the daily קרבן korban that the כהן גדול kohen gadol brings, the
חביתין chavitin that the כהן גדול kohen gadol brings? אלא מקיש חינוכו
להימשחו. ela makish chinucho lehimmashacho. It connects the initiation, the חינוך chinuch
of a normal כהן kohen to the anointing of a כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, which again it does not mean a one-time event although
it sounds like it; the anointing here means the status of the
כהן גדול kohen gadol being the anointed one and therefore bringing on
a daily basis his חביתין. chavitin. So what does that tell us?
מה המשחו רבוכה אף חינוכו רבוכה. mah hammashacho revucha af chinucho revucha.
The same way the כהן גדול's kohen gadol חביתין chavitin is this
רבוכה, revucha, there it says in the תורה, Torah, it says סלת
מורבכת, soles murbeches, or it says no, it says no, it says
מנחת פתים, minchas pisim, hold on רש"י Rashi quotes it. What does
it say by the כהן גדול? kohen gadol? It says מורבכת תביאנה
חלה תאפה. murbeches tevi'ennah chalah teafeh. No, not חלה תאפה. chalah teafeh.
Anyway, מורבכת תביאנה. murbeches tevi'ennah. So it used the word מורבכת, murbeches,
which means again this רבוכין, revuchin, what is, whatever that is, a
heavily oiled type of a loaf. So that is the כהן גדול's
kohen gadol חביתין. chavitin. Okay, so here what we're saying now is
remember, the whole point here is a historical point, what did the
כהנים kohanim bring when they brought their loaves of bread there when
they did the מילואים? Milu'in? identify two out of the three. We
don't know what the third one is. Now we're identifying the third
one because this פסוק Pasuk compares the bread—the bread that the כהן
Kohen brings when he is initiated into the עבודה Avodah to the
daily מנחה Mincha that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings יום המשחו.
Yom Himashcho. What's the daily מנחה Mincha that the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol brings? It is the חביתין Chavitin which we know from the
פסוק Pasuk is רבוכה. Revuachah. So therefore we learn that the normal
כהן's Kohen קרבן Korban when he was initiated included רבוכה. Revuachah. And
therefore since the פסוקים Pesukim are clear about the other two types,
from there we learn all of the three types that is brought
by a תודה. Todah. Okay, so let's see that. אלא מקיש חינוכו
להמשחו מה המשחו ברבוכה אף חינוכו ברבוכה. Ella makkish chinucho l'himashcho mah
himashcho b'revuachah af chinucho b'revuachah. So now we know that. We know
that the תורה's Torah explicit, it says three types of bread were
brought at the מילואים, Miluim, two it's very clear what they are,
they're the לחם Lechem and the רקיקים, Rekikin, and based on this
connection to the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol חביתין Chavitin we learn that
the third type is the רבוכה. Revuachah. Now we have a—we translate
this actually into something that's a little bit relevant past the wilderness
time. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
כהן גדול המתקרב לעבודה, Kohen Gadol hamitkarev la'avodah, if the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is drawing close to the עבודה, Avodah, funny phrase, but
it's using the phrase to mean it's his first time. First time
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is working. So the first time the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol works, צריך שתי עשרונות האיפה. tzarich shtei esronot
ha'eifah. He needs two עשרונות, esronot, two different מנחהs. Mincha Why? אחת
להמשחו, achat l'himashcho, one for his anointment stage, again that's the word
it uses for the daily מנחה Mincha that the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol would bring, the חביתין, Chavitin, the half in the morning half
in the afternoon, ואחת לחינוכו, v'achat l'chinucho, and because it's his first
day he has to bring the קרבן Korban to initiate him in
the עבודה. Avodah. So sort of totally incidentally without even explicitly saying
it, the גמרא Gemara transitioned from talking about a historical event about
when אהרן Aharon and his sons were initiated in the עבודה, Avodah,
which you would think, okay, that was a one-time thing, then the
כהנים Kohanim from that point afterwards were defined as designated for the
עבודה, Avodah, you don't need anything after that point to initiate them.
And nevertheless what do we learn out from there, we never even
really said it, we just sort of implied it, is using this
phrase of חינוכו chinucho is we learn out that when any כהן
Kohen begins his עבודה, Avodah, he begins with a מנחה Mincha to
initiate him into the עבודה. Avodah. And presumably this מנחה, Mincha, as
we just said, like the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol daily מנחה, Mincha,
this רבוכה. Revuachah. Okay, so therefore now saying, oh, so if it's
a כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol first day on the job, then he
brings two מנחות, Minchot, one for his daily מנחה, Mincha, his חביתין,
Chavitin, and one for his initiation מנחה. Mincha. And that's what he
would bring. No, every other כהן Kohen also brings a מנחה Mincha
on his first day on the job, but a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol has to bring two מנחות Minchot because he brings a מנחה
Mincha every day, his חביתין Chavitin every day. Right, and now the
גמרא Gemara says, this is the first day ever, not like first
day ever he started working, right, exactly. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar Rav Ashi, so מר Mar
the son of רב אשי Rav Ashi said, אמר שלש, amar shalosh,
three מנחות Minchot he'd have to bring. Three? ולא פליגי, v'lo pligi,
they don't argue. הא דעביד עבודה כשהוא כהן הדיוט הא דלא עביד
עבודה כשהוא כהן הדיוט. Ha d'avid avodah k'shehu Kohen Hedyot ha d'lo
avid avodah k'shehu Kohen Hedyot. What? It's the first day of his
job as what? Has he ever worked as a כהן Kohen before
in his life, or is it the very first time he's entering
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he's entering as a כהן גדול? Kohen
Gadol? Which, you know, could happen given what we know about the
second temple period, who got to be a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
So if he's before been a normal כהן Kohen and now he's
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he brings a special initiation קרבן Korban
to assume the role of כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and then he
brings this other קרבן Korban for his daily חביתין. Chavitin. But if
it's the first time he's ever served, he first has to bring
one קרבן Korban which initiates him as a כהן, Kohen, a next
קרבן Korban which initiates him as a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and
then a third one which is his daily obligatory קרבן. Korban. One
does wonder, you know, you would think they would have to be
sequential. It doesn't say that in the גמרא, Gemara, like you wonder
could I bring all three at the same time? You know you
can't be a convert and be a כהן. Kohen. That's a little
bit of a problem. Okay. Well, you might have gotten the office,
but you couldn't really be a כהן. Kohen. What? It's remarkable though,
I mean, to us the idea that—that they'd be so concerned with
what the procedure is for a guy like that, especially I mean,
it's a theoretical thing, right, fine, but it's—it's practical. Yeah, I think
the גמרא Gemara was more interested in it as a theory than
as like really... right. Yeah, I mean it was me that said
what's this כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doing on his first day on
the job ever, so I sort of brought it into the whole
second temple history, but I don't know if the גמרא Gemara is
having that in mind as much as just enjoying the theoretical question.
Okay, so that was a little bit of a—of a, you know,
I wouldn't say digression, but it was an application of this משנה
Mishnah which is just historical to at least some הלכה Halachah that
there is an idea of bringing a מנחה Mincha of initiation which
is not all thirty loaves, which is not all three types, it
is now the one type that's like the חביתין, Chavitin, it is
the רבוכה. Revuachah. But we did learn that the start—the first one
in the מדבר Midbar was all three types of מצה. Matzah. Now
we're talking... now we go on to נזירות. Nezirus. Nezirus נזירות, Nezirus,
I said for the two out of the three types of Matzah
מצה Matzah shebaTodah שבתודה, shebaTodah, and Nezirus נזירות Nezirus was two out
of the three types of Matzah מצה: Matzah: the Challos חלות Challos
and the Rakeikin רקיקין, Rakeikin, but not the Revucha רבוכה. Revucha. So
Tanna Rabbanan תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, so we taught in a Baraisa
ברייתא, Baraisa, Shlamav שלמיו, Shlamav, it says when it speaks about the
Todah תודה, Todah, it says al zevach todath shlamav על זבח תודת
שלמיו al zevach todath shlamav by the sacrifice of the Todah תודה
Todah of his Shlamim שלמים. Shlamim. So this extra word Shlamav שלמיו,
Shlamav, it didn't have to call it say Shlamav שלמיו, Shlamav, why
is it saying it? So this is a Baraisa ברייתא Baraisa that's
very often quoted, we saw it I think yesterday, l'rabos shalmei Nazir
לרבות שלמי נזיר, l'rabos shalmei Nazir, that it's coming to say that
the Todah תודה Todah sacrifice is Shlamav שלמיו Shlamav which connects to
other types of Shlamim שלמים. Shlamim. What Shlamim שלמים Shlamim is it
connecting to? The Shlamim שלמים Shlamim of a Nazir נזיר Nazir which
we also know has bread, but the Torah is not so clear
what type of bread you bring with the Shlamim שלמים Shlamim of
a Nazir נזיר. Nazir. So that's why we have this link, to
tell me l'asarah kavin Yerushalmios לעשרה קבין ירושלמיות, l'asarah kavin Yerushalmios, first
to tell me how much flour you use. Since it's the two
types of bread which is two-thirds of the normal amount of bread
you bring by the Todah תודה, Todah, so the normal bread of
a Todah תודה Todah is fifteen kavin קבין, kavin, here because it's
only two-thirds of that it is ten kavin קבין kavin like the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah said. Ul'revi'is shemen ולרביעית שמן, Ul'revi'is shemen, and also
the proportional amount of oil. How much oil do you use by
a Todah תודה? Todah? You use a revi'is רביעית revi'is for the
Challos חלות Challos and the and the Rakeikin רקיקין, Rakeikin, you use
another revi'is רביעית revi'is for the Revucha רבוכה. Revucha. So you know,
for the thirty loaves of Matzah מצה Matzah you have a half
of a log לוג. log. Revi'is רביעית, revi'is, remember, is what we
use for the shiur שיעור shiur for Kiddush קידוש, Kiddush, it's like
three and a half ounces. So we're not talking about a lot
of... Think about the amount of flour and then the amount of
oil, it's trivial. Like the amount of flour here is you know
ten we said ten bags for which you're going to have about
about seven ounces of oil. So you really need a lot of
water, you're basically using water, the oil is almost completely trivial. With
with that seven ounces of water half of it, a revi'is רביעית,
revi'is, goes to the Challos חלות Challos and the Rakeikin רקיקין Rakeikin
and the other half, the other three and a half ounces or
whatever, goes to the Revucha רבוכה. Revucha. So now the Challos חלות
Challos and the Rakeikin רקיקין Rakeikin are out of this ten kavin
קבין, kavin, no, six and two-thirds esronos עשרונות, esronos, and they are
out of this one revi'is רביעית, revi'is, this three and a half
ounces of oil. So that is what we apply now to the
Nazir נזיר. Nazir. The Nazir נזיר Nazir doesn't get the Revucha רבוכה
Revucha but he gets the Challos חלות Challos and the Rakeikin רקיקין
Rakeikin and therefore this amount of flour, that amount of oil. Okay.
Yakol l'chol mah she'amar b'inyan יכול לכל מה שאמר בענין, Yakol l'chol
mah she'amar b'inyan, maybe I apply everything to the Nazir נזיר Nazir
like maybe he even gets a Revucha רבוכה, Revucha, the the third
type of the loaf? Talmud lomar matzos תלמוד לומר מצות. Talmud lomar
matzos. So the Pasuk פסוק Pasuk says by the Nazir נזיר, Nazir,
sal matzos סל מצות. sal matzos. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says,
therefore he doesn't get a Revucha רבוכה. Revucha. So the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says mai talmuda מאי תלמודא, mai talmuda, where did you learn
you know what do you get out of that word? So amar
Rav Pappa אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, davar shenemar bo matzos
דבר שנאמר בו מצות, davar shenemar bo matzos, l'afukei Revucha d'lo nemar
bo matzos לאפוקי רבוכה דלא נאמר בו מצות. l'afukei Revucha d'lo nemar
bo matzos. It's actually a very lovely drasha דרשה. drasha. Right, how
does the Torah describe the three types of Matzah מצה Matzah by
the Todah תודה? Todah? It says challos matzos blulos bashemen urkikei matzos
meshuchim bashemen v'solet murbechet חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן
וסלת מרבכת. challos matzos blulos bashemen urkikei matzos meshuchim bashemen v'solet murbechet.
So when it gets to Revucha רבוכה Revucha it doesn't use the
word Matzah מצה. Matzah. And by the Nazir נזיר Nazir it says
he brings Matzah מצה. Matzah. So we have Nazir נזיר Nazir connected
to the Todah תודה, Todah, so the connection is going to tell
us apply the Matzah מצה Matzah types of bread to the Nazir
נזיר. Nazir. So while it's true the third thing also wasn't Chometz
חמץ, Chometz, but the word Matzah מצה Matzah wasn't used. And therefore
that's how we learn to apply the the normal loaves and the
and the Revucha רבוכה Revucha and the and the Rakeikin רקיקין Rakeikin
but not the Revucha רבוכה. Revucha. Okay, that's the answer. D'vei Rabbi
Yishmael tanna דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, D'vei Rabbi Yishmael tanna, Rabbi Yishmael
says matzos klal מצות כלל, matzos klal, he says no, you don't
have to make a whole gezeirah shavah גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. It's
in the Pasuk פסוק Pasuk by the Nazir נזיר. Nazir. The Nazir
נזיר, Nazir, by the Nazir נזיר Nazir it says sal matzos סל
מצות sal matzos and then it says specifically, it says Challos חלות
Challos and Rakeikin רקיקין, Rakeikin, we could open up a Pasuk פסוק,
Pasuk, maybe we should. Let me just quickly grab a Chumash חומש.
Chumash. And that's actually coming up, next week's Parsha פרשה Parsha is
Naso נשא. Naso. So, Nezirus נזירות. Nezirus. So let's take a look.
Smallest... it's the biggest Parsha פרשה Parsha in the whole Shas ש"ס
Shas in the whole Chumash חומש. Chumash. Yeah. So it says, here's
what it says here: v'hikriv et korbano l'Hashem keves ben shenato tamim
echad l'olah v'chivsah achat bat shenatah temimah l'chatat v'ayil echad tamim l'shlamim
והקריב את קרבנו לה' כבש בן שנתו תמים אחד לעלה וכבשה אחת
בת שנתה תמימה לחטאת ואיל אחד תמים לשלמים. v'hikriv et korbano l'Hashem
keves ben shenato tamim echad l'olah v'chivsah achat bat shenatah temimah l'chatat
v'ayil echad tamim l'shlamim. So one ram for a Shlamim שלמים, Shlamim,
so that's like Shlamim שלמים Shlamim is the same genre of a
Todah תודה, Todah, that's why we're going to make a gezeirah shavah
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of Shlamav שלמיו. Shlamav. And then it says,
v'sal matzos solet challos blulot bashemen v'rekikei matzos meshuchim bashemen וסל מצות
סלת חלות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן. v'sal matzos solet challos
blulot bashemen v'rekikei matzos meshuchim bashemen. It says it explicitly, it says
Challos חלות Challos and the Rakeikin רקיקין. Rakeikin. So it says it
explicitly. So why do you need to learn it out from a
you know learn it out from the Todah תודה, Todah, says Rabbi
Yishmael. D'vei Rabbi Yishmael tanna דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, D'vei Rabbi Yishmael
tanna, matzos klal מצות כלל, matzos klal, it says Matzos מצות Matzos
as a general, challos v'rekikin prat חלות ורקיקין פרט challos v'rekikin prat
and then it says explicitly Challos חלות Challos and Rakeikin רקיקין, Rakeikin,
klal u'prat ein b'klal ela mah shebaprat כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא
מה שבפרט. klal u'prat ein b'klal ela mah shebaprat. So we don't,
I don't need to go far afield to say why not to
say anything more than these two types. These are the two types
mentioned in the פסוק. pasuk. That's all. אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט.
ein baklal ela mah sheba'prat. חלות ורקיקים אין, יש חלות ורקיקים, מידי
אחריני לא, challot v'rekikim in, yesh challot v'rekikim, midi achrini lo, nothing
else. So תוספות Tosafot actually makes an interesting point that people often
ask. The principle of כלל ופרט klal u'prat is אין בכלל אלא
מה שבפרט. ein baklal ela mah sheba'prat. If the Torah says a
general statement and then specifically enumerates, then don't broaden it, then it's
only the things enumerated. So the question everybody asks is, so then
why did it have to say the general statement? Just explicitly say:
here are the things that you bring. So תוספות Tosafot here says
that it could be that by saying it general and then saying
it specific, it's specifically to tell you only this and nothing else.
That if it had just enumerated, you might have thought, well, other
things as well that are similar to it. And he says that's
the point this גמרא Gemara is making, because the גמרא Gemara is
saying maybe I should say the נזיר nazir brings two types, but
I'll learn out from a תודה Todah that you bring a third
type as well. And the answer is no, the כלל ופרט klal
u'prat tells you only these two and nothing else. Okay, so it
makes a general statement but then after it says, "And here's what
I mean, just these two." Okay, so that's how you know those
two. So the idea that that's what a נזיר nazir brings we
know, so what is it then that we learn out from the
תודה? Todah? We learn about the amount of flour and the amount
of oil. That what you bring is explicit in the פסוק, pasuk,
but the amount of flour we learn out from the תודה Todah
that it is these ten קבים. kavim. Okay, now, we are done
with making the loaves of bread for the תודה Todah and all
of the ingredients. We turn the page and we can actually talk
a little bit about something about conceptually how those loaves are connected
to the תודה Todah and how they become sanctified. Let's now look
at the משנה Mishnah on ע"ח עמוד ב. ayin-chet amud bet. השוחט
את התודה לפנים ולחמה חוץ לחומה. hashocheit et hatodah lifnim v'lachmah chutz
lachomah. So here you have a very fascinating question, because the תודה
Todah is קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. קדשים קלים kodashim kalim can be
eaten in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so what and but we
also assume that the slaughtering of the תודה Todah sanctifies the bread,
brings it to its full level of sanctity. Now it's a little
funny because when you have a normal מנחה, minchah, you have no
קרבן korban that raises the sanctity of the מנחה, minchah, the מנחה
minchah is קדוש kadosh on its own terms. And there the question
is, does it become קדוש kadosh when it's placed in the כלי,
kli, at what stage is there a כלי, kli, is it the
oven, is it a כלי שרת kli shareit and so on. By
a bread of a תודה, Todah, because they're linked to a קרבן,
korban, their full קדושה kedushah is only achieved when the קרבן korban
is slaughtered. The question is where is the bread? Because for the
bread to get קדושה, kedushah, it has to be within a holy
place. So the משנה Mishnah says that if the bread is outside
if the קרבן korban is inside the מקדש Mikdash and the bread
is outside of the wall, לא קידש הלחם, lo kideish halechem, it
doesn't become sanctified. Now presumably this means outside of the wall of
the מקדש, Mikdash, because the לפנים lifnim of the קרבן korban means
in the מקדש. Mikdash. So even so therefore the קרבן korban the
bread has to be if it's going to be sanctified and seen
as one with the קרבן korban and sanctified through the bringing of
the קרבן, korban, it has to be in the מקדש. Mikdash. That's
פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishnah, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
a different possible read of this. When it says in the פשט
pshat the חומה chomah is what? חומת העזרה, chomat ha'azarah, the wall
of the עזרה. Azarah. It was a wall? Yeah, meaning the whole
מקדש Mikdash was a wall and then when you walked into the
עזרה Azarah from the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, there was a wall
in front of you and a door and you had to go
through there was the שער ניקנור. Shaar Nikanor. Yeah, exactly, exactly, to
pass through the wall from the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim to the
עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. So it means outside of the שער ניקנור.
Shaar Nikanor. Right, exactly. Exactly. Okay, now similarly because about the way
the bread was sanctified, if you slaughter the קרבן korban עד שלא
קרמו פניה בתנור, ad shelo karmu paneha batanur, before the crust has
somehow hardened, become a crust in the oven, it's not yet considered
bread. So it has to have a developed a crust in the
oven. ואפילו קרמו כולן חוץ מאחד מהן, va'afilu karmu kulan chutz mi'echad
meihen, and even if all of the loaves got a crust except
for one and it's still baking and just one of those loaves
is not yet fully bread, לחם, lechem, which it needs to have
a crust to be considered that, so לא קידש הלחם, lo kideish
halechem, then the bread does not become sanctified. Okay, so you have
to so the משנה Mishnah here is a very important משנה, Mishnah,
teaches the slaughtering of the קרבן korban sanctifies the bread, the bread
has to be bread, it has to have a crust, all of
the loaves have to be bread, and it has to be inside.
So the גמרא Gemara will first turn itself to the question of
what does inside mean? מאי חוץ לחומה, mai chutz lachomah, what type
of outside of the wall is a problem? What wall are we
referring to? רבי יוחנן אמר חוץ לחומת בית פאגי, Rabbi Yochanan amar
chutz lachomat Beit Pagi, outside of the wall of בית פאגי. Beit
Pagi. Not exactly clear what בית פאגי Beit Pagi is, it's certainly
not the wall of the עזרה. Azarah. There is a רש"י Rashi
somewhere that says it means it's a wall around the הר הבית,
Har Habayit, which actually would be like the כותל. Kotel. That everybody's
people I think think that the כותל Kotel was like the wall
of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash but it's not, it's the wall
around the הר הבית. Har Habayit. Anyway, but more simply בית פאגי
Beit Pagi means a wall the outer wall of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
it means outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That's רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Anywhere
in ירושלים Yerushalayim you're okay with the bread, outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim
is a problem. ריש לקיש אמר חוץ לחומת העזרה. Reish Lakish amar
chutz lachomat ha'azarah. No, no, no, we mean outside of the wall.
wall of the עזרה, Azarah, it has to be in the עזרה
Azarah proper. So let's take a look at what this debate is
about. So ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, so בעינן על בסמוך.
be'inan al besamoch. על Al means really next to because when the
תורה Torah describes bringing it, it says על חלות לחם חמץ יביא
קרבנו, al challos lechem chametz yavi korbano, bring it with the loaves
of חמץ. chametz. So with means literally together. So if the תודה
Todah have to be in the עזרה, Azarah, you can't שחט shecht
the תודה Todah outside of the עזרה, Azarah, then you have to
have the bread together with it. And that makes a conceptual sense
because the bread gets sanctified together with the קרבן, korban, it has
to be somehow like it's being brought with the קרבן, korban, and
has to be in the עזרה. Azarah. That's what ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, which I would suggest is פשט pshat of the משנה.
Mishnah. Let's see what רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says. רבי יוחנן אמר,
Rebbe Yochanan amar, I'm sorry, I misread, ריש לקיש אמר חוץ לחומת
העזרה. Reish Lakish amar chutz l'chomas ha-azarah. ריש לקיש אמר חוץ לחומת
העזרה, Reish Lakish amar chutz l'chomas ha-azarah, why, why does it have
to be as soon as you get outside of the מקדש Mikdash
is it a problem? בעינן be'inan על בסמוך. al besamoch. When it
says על חלות לחם חמץ, al challos lechem chametz, then it means
really literally next to it in order to be sanctified with it,
and that's what the word על al means. רבי יוחנן אמר חוץ
לחומת בית פאגי. Rebbe Yochanan amar chutz l'chomas beis pagi. No, it's
only a problem if it's out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אבל חוץ לעזרה,
Aval chutz l'azarah, but if it's out of the עזרה, Azarah, קדוש,
kadosh, it is sanctified. ולא בעינן על בסמוך, V'lo be'inan al besamoch,
we do not need, when it says together with the חמץ, chametz,
it does not mean literally the חמץ chametz has to be in
the same place. Okay, now it is, you know, רש"י Rashi and
what am I, the תוספות, Tosafos, and the שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzos
bring up a point that a lot of this is contextual, like
when the גמרא Gemara spoke about waving the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
with the two כבשים, kevasim, there you know, there it did talk
more about them being in the מקדש Mikdash and waving it together
and so on. But the point here is, okay, but here you're
not מקריב makriv yet the bread, you're slaughtering the קרבן. korban. So
maybe it doesn't have to be in the מקדש. Mikdash. If you
were conceptually offering the bread, it would have to be in the
עזרה. Azarah. But if you're actually not offering the bread, you're just
slaughtering the קרבן korban and the bread is becoming קדוש, kadosh, then
maybe it doesn't have to be in the עזרה. Azarah. Now this
is though very important. The only reason it's possible the bread is
outside of the עזרה Azarah for רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan is because
it's קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Right, all מנחות minchos are קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodshim. They could never be outside of the עזרה. Azarah. So
if you're talking about them becoming קדוש, kadosh, they have to be
in the עזרה Azarah cause then they don't leave the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. All מנחות minchos are קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodshim. The only
quasi-מנחה mincha that is not קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim are the breads
of a תודה. Todah. That's קדשים קלים kodshim kalim like the תודה
Todah itself and that can be in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
therefore רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says look, if this bread can be
eaten in all ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it could become קדוש kadosh in all
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It doesn't have to be in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So let it be anywhere in ירושלים Yerushalayim and the slaughtering
of the קרבן korban will sanctify the bread even if they're not
next to each other. That's what רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says. So
now the גמרא Gemara says ואיפלגו בה חדא זימנא, v'ifligu bah chada
zimna, they argued about a similar thing in a different place, previously,
not by this, but regarding שחט shechting קרבן פסח Korban Pesach על
חמץ. al chametz. It says לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי. lo
sishchat al chametz dam zivchi. Again, the על. al. Don't slaughter my
פסח Pesach over חמץ. chametz. So what does על al mean? Where
is the חמץ chametz have to be for you to transgress? דתנן,
D'tnan, we learned in a משנה, Mishnah, השוחט את הפסח על החמץ,
hashochet es hapesach al hachametz, if somebody slaughters a פסח Pesach over
חמץ, chametz, what over חמץ chametz means, over בלא תעשה, b'lo sa'aseh,
you transgress the negative prohibition in the תורה. Torah. רבי יהודה אומר
אף התמיד, Rabbi Yehuda omer af hatamid, even if you slaughtered the
תמיד Tamid of the afternoon תמיד Tamid of ערב פסח, Erev Pesach,
even if you slaughtered that when you still owned חמץ, chametz, you
also transgress. Okay, that's not our interest, why he included the תמיד,
Tamid, but that's not our interest. Our interest is where is the
חמץ? chametz? ואמר ריש לקיש לעולם אינו חייב, V'amar Reish Lakish l'olam
eino chayav, you don't transgress slaughtering your פסח Pesach over חמץ chametz
עד שיהא, ad sheyehei, until there is או לשוחט, o lashochet, first
of all, who has the חמץ? chametz? Either the one who did
the slaughtering, anybody involved in it. Either the one who did the
slaughtering, או לזורק, o lazorek, the one sprinkling the blood, the כהן,
Kohen, או לאחד מבני החבורה, o l'echad mibnei hachaburah, or one of
the owners. So who will transgress if you have חמץ? chametz? If
number one, who has חמץ? chametz? Either an owner or somebody who
is doing one of the עבודות. avodas. That means that you had
חמץ chametz when you were offering. That's the who has חמץ. chametz.
Now where is the חמץ? chametz? So לאחד מבני l'echad mibnei and
then it says עמו בעזרה. imo ba'azarah. And the bread has to
be with the שוחט shochet or the זורק zorek or the owner
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, in the actual עזרה. Azarah. So
על חמץ al chametz means the bread is right there, the חמץ
chametz is right there in the עזרה. Azarah. That's ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish's interpretation of על. al. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebbe Yochanan amar, רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says no, אף על פי שאינו עמו בעזרה. af
al pi she'eino imo ba'azarah. I agree those are the people who
it matters that they have חמץ chametz or not, but their חמץ
chametz could be in their home, it doesn't have to be in
the עזרה. Azarah. It could be in Tel Aviv, but if you're
the owner of the פסח Pesach and you're bringing your פסח Pesach
and you still own חמץ chametz back in Tel Aviv, then you're
transgressing לא תשחט על חמץ. lo sishchat al chametz. It doesn't have
to be with the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, literally with. Correct, exactly.
That's the question: is על al mean literally with or conceptually connected
to? So why did they debate both cases, what על al means?
So the גמרא Gemara says צריכא, tzricha, you need both cases. דאי
איתמר בהא, Di imar bahai, if it had just said about the
case by פסח Pesach and חמץ, chametz, בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן, bahai
ka'amar Rebbe Yochanan, דכל היכא דאית ביה איסורא כי... dechol heicha de'isbei
issur k'ei... Who needs the חמץ chametz to be right on top
of the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Wherever it is, you're transgressing, wherever
it is, you're owning חמץ chametz when you shouldn't be owning חמץ.
chametz. So why do I care that it's right there with the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach or not? אבל לענין מקדש לחם, aval l'inyan
mikadesh lechem, but here where the slaughtering of the קרבן korban gives
sanctity to the bread, אימא מודה ליה לריש לקיש, eima modi lei
l'Reish Lakish, maybe he would agree to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דאית
בפנים קדוש, d'is bifnim kadosh, if it's together inside with the קרבן,
korban, the sanctity, it becomes sanctified, אבראי ומחוץ למחיצה לא קדוש, avrai
u'michutz l'mechitzah lo kadosh, not, which makes a tremendous amount of sense,
right? One idea is don't be have חמץ chametz while you're slaughtering
it. And the other is, if you want it to somehow the
act done to the קרבן korban somehow relates to the bread, you
want the bread to be right there. Okay, so therefore you had
to tell me that he argues in both cases. ואי איתמר בהא,
v'ei itmar beha, if we had just said our case about the
תודה, Toda, בהא קאמר ריש לקיש, beha ka'amar Reish Lakish, that's where
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that they have to be together for
it to be sanctified, אבל בהך דחמץ, aval behach d'chametz, but by
חמץ, chametz, אימא מודה ליה לרבי יוחנן, eima modi lei l'Rabbi Yochanan,
maybe he would agree to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. צריכא, tzricha, so
therefore it needs both cases. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, tanya kvatei d'Rabbi
Yochanan, we learned a ברייתא braita like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, surprisingly,
although the logic seems to be ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. השוחט את
התודה בפנים ולחמה חוץ לחומת בית פאגי, hashocheit es haToda bifnim v'lachmah
chutz l'chomas Beis Pagi, לא קידש הלחם. lo kideish halechem. If you
slaughtered the תודה Toda and the bread was outside of בית פאגי,
Beis Pagi, again, we'll assume it's outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, then it
does not become sanctified. So you see that that is like רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that anywhere it's in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the slaughtering of
the תודה Toda sanctifies the bread. It doesn't have to be literally
with it in the עזרה. Azarah. So that's principle number one: the
slaughtering of the תודה Toda sanctifies the bread. The bread has to
be somehow connected to it. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it
doesn't mean in the עזרה, Azarah, but at least it has to
be in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, because remember, the bread cannot be eaten out
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, it cannot be taken out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Now we get to the fact that it has to be bread
when the animal is slaughtered. It has to have developed a crust.
So let's take a look. קרמו פניה בתנור. karmu paneha b'tanur. If
the face of it has sort of crusted in the oven. שחטה
עד שלא קרמו פניה, shachatah ad shelo karmu paneha, if you slaughtered
it before it's crusted, then it is not considered sanctified because it's
not yet bread. מנא הני מילי, mana hani mili, where do you
know this from? דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabanan, we taught, על חלת לחם
חמץ יקריב קרבנו, al chalas lechem chametz yakriv korbano, on loaves of
bread of חמץ chametz you should bring the קרבן, korban, על זבח,
al zevach, on the slaughtering. So here we have the slaughtering connected
to the loaves of חמץ. chametz. מלמד שאינו לחם קדוש אלא אם
כן קרמו פניה בתנור. melamed she'eino lechem kadosh ela im kein karmu
paneha b'tanur. The bread does not become sanctified at the slaughtering, that's
the על זבח, al zevach, unless it developed a crust because without
a crust it's not considered לחם. lechem. Okay, so that's the key,
although it didn't spell it out, the assumption here is that you
need it to have a crust for it to be considered לחם.
lechem. And now interestingly, we're going to turn to other cases where
the concept of לחם lechem is relevant. יקריב קרבנו, yakriv korbano, you
should bring his קרבן, korban, על זבח, al zevach, on the slaughtering.
מלמד שאין הלחם קדוש אלא בשחיטת הזבח. melamed she'ein halechem kadosh ela
b'shechitas hazevach. And that tells us that you bring the bread on
the slaughtering and on the קרבן korban and on the slaughtering, that
is, the slaughtering of the קרבן korban that sanctifies the bread. שאין
הלחם קדוש אלא בשחיטת הזבח. she'ein halechem kadosh ela b'shechitas hazevach. So
and now זבח תודתו, zevach todaso, the זבח zevach of his תודה.
Toda. מלמד שאם שחטה שלא לשמה לא קידש הלחם. melamed she'im shachatah
shelo lishmah lo kideish halechem. So it's a slaughtering of the תודה.
Toda. If you slaughtered it not as a תודה, Toda, then the
bread does not become sanctified, which makes a lot of sense because
if remember the general principles of שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, the קרבן
korban is כשר, kasher, לא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה. lo ala l'ba'alim
l'shem chovah. Here it's maybe taking that a little step further and
it's saying if it's not לשם תודה, l'shem Toda, we can't really
fully consider it a תודה. Toda. We can maybe consider it a
שלמים Shlamim and let it be brought or whatever, but it doesn't
have the full status of a תודה Toda and therefore it does
not sanctify the bread. The bread only comes with a full תודה.
Toda. So when you שחט shacht שלא לשם תודה, shelo l'shem Toda,
it does not sanctify. So this פסוק, pasuk, על זבח, al zevach,
is the core of the principle that the slaughtering of the קרבן
korban sanctifies the bread. The bread is על זבח, al zevach, only
when it's slaughtered as a תודה, Toda, and it has to be
לחם, lechem, it has to have a crust. And now we're going
to focus on the crust. Okay, so let's take a look. תנו
רבנן, tanu rabanan, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. יוצאין במצה, yotzin
b'matzah, this is a ברייתא braita by פסח, Pesach, by what you
are יוצא yotzei for the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah בליל סדר.
b'leil Seder. יוצאין במצה נא, yotzin b'matzah na, even if it's somewhat
not fully cooked. נא na is often translated as raw, but the
גמרא Gemara understands that נא na does not mean raw, it means,
you know, לא תאכלו ממנו נא lo sochlu mimenu na by the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, it means not fully cooked. Okay, so you
could use, you could be יוצא yotzei with מצה matzah that has
not been that's half-baked. ובמצה העשויה באילפס, u'v'matzah ha'asuyah b'ilpas, and even
מצה matzah made in a pot, not made in an oven, you
know, you basically stuck it to the walls of the pot and
you cooked it in a pot. Like a pita? Okay, something like
that. Okay, so מאי מצה נא, mai matzah na, what is uncooked
מצה? matzah? Meaning the really the question is how cooked does it
have to be to in order to minimally be כשר? kasher? So
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, כל שפורסה
ואין חוטין נמשכין הימנה. kol sheporsah v'ein chutin nimshachin heimena. When you
break... It doesn't have the strands that are stretching from it, which
means that it's still doughy on the inside. If it's still doughy
on the inside and you break it and you still have the
strands of dough, that is not considered cooked enough to be considered
מצה. matza. Now, that's going to be also relevant for the תודה,
toda, because all of these things we know that they have to
be considered bread from the word לחם, lechem, and we're assuming that
that לחם lechem is the same definition. So whatever's defined as bread
for מצה matza is for תודה toda and vice versa. Okay, so
let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, וכן לענין לחמי תודה,
vechen le-inyan lachmei toda, the same is true about תודה, toda, that
for in order for it to be considered bread, when you break
it, it can't have the doughy thing stretching. Some also say that
what רבא Rava is doing is he's trying to say that that's
the same שיעור shiur as the קרמו פניה. karmeu paneha. When our
משנה mishna mentions the crusting, he's saying what is the crusting? Here's
basically another measure for that, that when you break it, you don't
have the strands stretching from it. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously it's the same.
הכא לחם כתיב והכא לחם כתיב. Hacha lechem ketiv ve-hacha lechem ketiv.
It says לחם lechem by both cases. מהו דתימא, Mahudeiteima, אחד אמר
רחמנא, echad amar Rachmana, שלא יטופרס. shelo yitopares. Remember we said you
give one loaf of each ten to the כהן, kohen, not a
half loaf. והא כמאן דפריס דמי. Ve-ha keman de-paris dami. And even
if it's not fully cooked, even if it's no longer strandy, if
it's not fully cooked, it'll crumble more easy, it doesn't really retain
its shape so well, and therefore maybe it's a broken piece. So
maybe it's not valid. So therefore he's telling you קא משמע לן,
ka mashma lan, that's not a concern. Once it's bread, it's bread,
and now we have two different measures of bread: a crust, maybe
you need both, maybe they're different measures, a crust, and when you
break it you don't have doughy strands still being pulled. Okay. איתמר.
Itmar. תודה ששחטה. Toda she-shachata. One last issue about this. Let's see,
do we have time to get into this or not? Two minutes.
Alright, let's try to do it quickly. איתמר. Itmar. תודה ששחטה על
שמונים חלות. Toda she-shachata al shemonim chalot. Instead of bringing forty חלות,
chalot, you brought eighty חלות. chalot. What's going to happen? Nothing, everything?
Let's take a look. חזקיה אמר קידשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Chizkiya amar
kidshu arbaim mitoch shemonim. Forty of the loaves become sanctified. Okay, so
you slaughtered it. Again, this is all because the slaughtering creates the
sanctity. So you sanctified eighty, or you didn't sanctify, you said here
are my loaves, and you did the slaughtering. What does the slaughtering
do when there's too many loaves? So he says forty of them
are sanctified. You don't know which forty, but so you have to
eat all of them לחומרא, le-chumra, within a day and eat it
all in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, etc., but forty are sanctified and you're יוצא.
yotzei. רבי יוחנן אמר לא קידשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Rabbi Yochanan amar
lo kidshu arbaim mitoch shemonim. No, you tried to do eighty, you
got zero, because it doesn't work for eighty, and therefore none are
sanctified, and therefore you're not יוצא yotzei the תודה, toda, because it's
a תודה toda without the bread. So none of them became sanctified.
אמר רבי זירא. Amar Rabbi Zeira. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira explains.
הכל מודים היכא דאמר ליקדשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Hakol modin heicha de-amar
likdeshu arbaim mitoch shemonim. If you were explicit and said, I want
forty out of the eighty to be sanctified, קידשו, kidshu, it works.
You don't know which forty, but at least it works and you're
יוצא. yotzei. אל יקדשו ארבעים אלא אם כן יקדשו שמונים. Al yikdeshu
arbaim ella im ken yikdeshu shemonim. If you say, I don't want
forty to be sanctified, it's all or nothing, exactly, I want them
all or none of it to be sanctified, לא קידשו. lo kidshu.
Then nothing is sanctified because the תורה Torah only recognized forty loaves.
So כי פליגי, ki pligi, what's the debate? בסתמא. Bis-tama. You didn't
say what you intended. מר סבר לאחריות קמכוין. Mar savar leachrayut kamichaven.
One of them holds, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, that it's good, you
really only wanted forty, the other forty were a backup in case
the first forty somehow got lost. ומר סבר לקרבן גדול קמכוין. U-mar
savar le-korban gadol kamichaven. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, no if
you're bringing eighty, you want all eighty, and therefore since it doesn't
work for all eighty, nothing works, literally. Okay. אביי אמר. Abaye amar.
So now two other suggestions as to what the debate is. אביי
Abaye says, דכולי עלמא לקרבן גדול קמכוין. dekuli alma le-korban gadol kamichaven.
We'll go with the side girsa. Everybody is saying you're trying to
do all eighty. Okay. If that's true, why does ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish say it still works if you're trying to do all eighty?
ובכלי שרת מקדשין שלא מדעת קמיפלגי. U-vikhli sharet mekadeshin shelo mida-at kamifligi.
The question is whether the כלי שרת, kli sharet, here interestingly the
כלי שרת kli sharet is not the vessel that you made the
מנחה mincha in, but the סכין sakin of שחיטה, shechita, because that's
bringing the sanctity to the bread. So you שחט shachat the קרבן,
korban, does that sanctity now that applies to the bread, does that
work regardless of what you're thinking? Now, normally we say it means
you don't have to be thinking anything for it to work. But
here it means it overrides what you're thinking. You're trying to sanctify
all eighty, but who cares what you're thinking? The כלי שרת kli
sharet operates on its own, and it's going to sanctify regardless of
what you're thinking, and it'll sanctify forty because it works for forty.
Okay. מר סבר כלי שרת מקדשין שלא מדעת. Mar savar kli sharet
mekadeshin shelo mida-at. It sanctifies regardless of what you're thinking, and it
works for forty, whichever forty. ומר סבר כלי שרת אין מקדשין אלא
מדעת. U-mar savar kli sharet ein mekadeshin ella mida-at. No, it only
works based on what you're thinking, and if you want eighty, it's
only going to work for eighty, but it doesn't work for eighty,
so therefore it's zero. Okay. רב פפא אמר דכולי עלמא כלי שרת
מקדשין שלא מדעת. Rav Papa amar dekuli alma kli sharet mekadeshin shelo
mida-at. No, everybody says that it would operate on its own. והכא
בסכין קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-sakin kamifligi. The question is the power of the
knife. Does that work like a normal כלי שרת? kli sharet? Okay.
מר סבר סכין מקדש ככלי שרת. Mar savar sakin mekadesh kekhli sharet.
It works like any כלי שרת, kli sharet, and it does it
on its own, and therefore regardless of what you're thinking, forty become
קדוש. kadosh. ומר סבר... U-mar savar... סכין כיון דלית ליה תוך אינו
מקדש ככלי שרת. Sakin keivan d'leis lei toch eino mekadesh kekli shares.
A knife doesn't have a container, you know, it's a knife. So
therefore it's not a standard כלי שרת. k'li shares. A standard כלי
שרת k'li shares is like a bowl and therefore you put something
in it, it defines the thing inside of it, right? To say
that you שחט shecht with a knife and that sanctifies the other
thing conceptually is very different than if you have a container and
you put it in a container that the container defines it. Right.
And you could go even further. The knife is שחטינג shechting the
animal, so it's even further removed than the bread. So I might
say a normal כלי שרת k'li shares operates on its own but
not the knife. And therefore it only goes by what you're thinking,
and what you're thinking is eighty and therefore it's no good. Last
answer. Does it do nothing again? Then it, oh, that's a good
question, whether שלא מדעת shelo mida'as means only if you're in conflict
or even if it... you might even really require it to be
conscious about it. I'd have to check. The איכא דאמרי eika de'amre
let's just finish we're already way over. רב פפא אמר דכולי עלמא
כלי שרת אין מקדשין אלא מדעת. Rav Pappa amar dechulei alma k'li
shares ein mekadeshin ela mida'as. It requires דעת da'as normally. So if
it requires דעת da'as you have a דעת da'as of eighty that's
gonna ruin it. והכא בסכין קמיפלגי. Vehacha besakin kamipalgei. Maybe the knife
is more powerful than a normal כלי שרת. k'li shares. מר סבר
סכין אלימא מכלי שרת. Mar savar sakin alima mikli shares. That exactly
what you said is its weakness is its strength, it's stronger than
a כלי שרת. k'li shares. דאף על גב דלית ליה תוך מקדש.
De'af al gav d'leis lei toch mekadesh. Once we admit that the
knife sanctifies without being a container, what we're saying is that it's
more powerful than a normal כלי שרת. k'li shares. It works in
ways a normal כלי שרת k'li shares doesn't. And therefore it will
work regardless of what you're thinking. ומר סבר סכין לא אלימא ליה
מכל שאר שרת. Umar savar sakin lo alima lei mikol sh'ar shares.
It is not more powerful. So this is a great גמרא, Gomora,
little גמרא Gomora here at the end, it's a little bad we
had to rush through it. Not only the idea that it can't
be eighty, it has to be forty, but the question is about
how the vessel sanctifies, the possible difference between a knife and a
container, which is stronger, which is weaker, and also the question about
whether it matters what you're thinking or whether they operate on their
own.